<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Proposition of the Ambassadour Peckius, in the congregation of the General States with the answer of the sayd General States, the xxv. of March, 1621 / translated, out of Dutch, according to the copy, printed by Aert Meurs, bookseller in the Hague.</title>
            <author>Peck, Pierre, 1562-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18460.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2827</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">25207658</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 25207658</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27881</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08100)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1857:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Proposition of the Ambassadour Peckius, in the congregation of the General States with the answer of the sayd General States, the xxv. of March, 1621 / translated, out of Dutch, according to the copy, printed by Aert Meurs, bookseller in the Hague.</title>
                  <author>Peck, Pierre, 1562-1625.</author>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Printed abroad."--Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Twelve Years' Truce, 1609-1621.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27881:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:27881:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
PROPOSITION <hi>Of the Ambaſſadour</hi> PECKIVS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Congregation of the General States.</hi> WITH THE ANSVVER Of the ſayd General States, the XXV. of March, 1621.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>TRANSLATED, Out of Dutch, according to the Copy, printed by AERT MEURS, Bookſeller in the HAGUE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letters_of_credence">
            <pb facs="tcp:27881:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A COPIE</hi> Of the Letters of Credence.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>LOvinge Freends, vvee ſend thither Sr. Pieter Peckius, Lord Knight of Bouc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout, &amp;c. Counſeler of our Counſel of State, and Chanceler of Brabant bringher of this, to handle with you of certayne cauſe that hee ſhall declare unto you: And therefore this ſhal ſerve to require, not onely to give him good audience, but alſo to give him full credit in that hee ſhall declare unto you from our Part. Lovinge Freends vvee commende you in the mercifull Protection of the Almighty God. In Bruſſel the 16 of March, 1621.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Subſcribed Albert and Iſabel.</signed>
               <signed>Lower. Verreycken.</signed>
               <salute>The Superſcription,
<hi>To our Lovinge Freends the General States of the Vnited Provinces.</hi>
               </salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proposition">
            <pb facs="tcp:27881:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROPOSITION</hi> Of the Ambaſſadour <hi>PECKIVS.</hi> In the Congregation of the General States.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OBLE &amp; MIGHTY LORDS,</hi> Theſe latter dayes of the Truce of twelf years of the Lowe Countreys / our common Fatherland / do ſet before our eyes the lamentable mutation commonly following after ſuch temporall Agreements / and whereof the preparations on both ſides are promooved and advaunced al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. But the Archidukes looking with a pittifull eye upon the extreame and moſt deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Inconveniences and miſeries / wherein this Lands thorough / this mutation ſhould come to falle / could not chooſe to bring into great conſideration the meanes fit / expedient and required to the preventing and averting of them / ſpecially beeinge mooved to this health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſalutary ſentence / thorough their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination to Peace / and thorough their zeale and affection to the commune wealth / which likewiſe hath beene the cheefeſt and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal motives / that their Highneſſes have reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb facs="tcp:27881:3"/>
to the ſayd Truce / as a beginning of the whole deſired tranquillitie and reſt / and of the Quenching of the Flame of warre / wherein at their cominge they found theſe Lands / thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that within the time of the ſame Truce / there actions have klearly and manifeſtly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and declared the ſurety of their good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion / and for this future time their Highneſſes have nothing more carefully beharted / then to procure the greateſt advantage of theſe Lands in Generall / which ſeemes to conſiſte therein that all the Parts and Members of the Low Countreys ſhould gather in one body and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one head / beeing apparent / that as they where before the troubles in peaceable union and quiet proſperitie / they ſhould yet more uſe and enioye the ſame if the Provinces of this ſide / would conſent to a good / and firme Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with acknowledge of their Natural Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. This is the Poinct that their Highneſſes have charged mee to declare unto your Mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and freendly to preſent / ſuppoſing that it was their duety and required office of good Princes before all breaches of warre / ſeeking and beharting your owne continuall welfare and proſperitie / and that conſideration ſhould be taken of it / with a fruitfull reſolution / by which all ſheading of blood / exceeding chardges and other lamentable miſeries (whereunto this Low Countreys have beene ſubiect ſo many yeares) once might be avoyded: And if your Mightineſſes would come / upon this condition
<pb facs="tcp:27881:3"/>
to a communication of Agreement / their High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſhall incline to ſuch reoſonnable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and capitulations / that the ſame your High Mightineſſes ſhall have full reaſon of good contentement / and ſee not onely the affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the good will of their Highneſſes / but eke the equitie and ſinceritie / which alwayes they have had in ſundry recommendation / and manifeſtly declared hitherto by the punctuel and religious keeping of all their actions and promiſes / as that ſame ſufficiently may bee tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted unto them: Aſſuring your High Mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes likewiſe of the like good and ſincere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Catholike Maieſtie / and that the ſame ſhall have for good / firme and acceptable / what their Highneſſes concerning this cauſe ſhal do and conclude.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And was ſubſcribed P. PECKIUS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:27881:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ANSVVER</hi> Vpon the ſayd Propoſition / of the ſayd High / Mighty Lords the States of the Vnited Lowe Countreys.</head>
            <p>THe General States of the Vnited Lowe Countreys having heard and througly examined the Propoſition from the Part of the Archidukes / in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their High Mightineſſes / firſt verbolly done / and thereafter delivered in writing by the Lord Petro Peckio Knight of Bouchoute / Canceler of Brabant / by power of Lettres of Credencie of the ſayd Archidukes / dated in Bruſſel the 16 of this Moneth. Declare that the Highneſſe and Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigntie of the Vnited Lowe Countries is ſure / and with out any contraverſy by their High Mightineſſes / and by the States of the Reſpective Provinces / that they have maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alwayes religiouſly the ſame / againſt al thoſe that would bring it in doubt / or to undertake any thing againſt the ſame / or appropriate it to any other Princes / and conſequently that they never would come to any treatiſes or agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts / wheere by the ſame ſhould have beene brought in any doubt / where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they have given expres declaration to the Emperour / Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours and Princes / and other Potentates / and likewiſe to the ſayd Archidukes / that the State of their High Mightineſſes is holden Souverain / and their Lands for free Lands ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged and accepted by the greateſt Monarches / Kings / Potentates and Republiques / who all / in the ſame qualitie / have made with their High. Migh. ſundry treatiſes / and Confederations / having likewiſe maintained it ſo farre / that their High Mightineſſes / nor with the ſayde Archiduke / nor with the King of Spaine / would not undertake any Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / before the ſame had given an acte of Declaration of it / that they did handle with the ſame their High Mightineſſes / as with free Lands and Provinces whereupon they had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to pretende: And becauſe that ſame is as kleare as the Noonedaye / and manifeſtly knowen to all the world / therefore their High Mightineſſes hold very ſtraunge the Propoſition of the Lord Chanceler <hi>PECKIO,</hi> declaringe that the greateſt advantage of theſe Lands ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte therein / that all the Parts and membres of the Lowe
<pb facs="tcp:27881:4"/>
Countreys ſhould gather in one body and under one Head / and that they would conſent to a good and Firme Agreement with acknow: of theyr natural Princes / if the ſame lands upon this condition would come to a communicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / that theyr Higneſſes ſhould incline to reaſonnable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: Becauſe the ſame Condition could not ſerve to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventinge and aboydinge of the extreame inconveniences / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein the Lands thorough the warres againe ſhould come to falle / whereunto the Propoſition ſeemes to ſtretche / but rather ſhall kindle the fyer of warre / becauſe it goes directly againſt the ſayd confeſſed ſouveraigntie and Highneſſe of the Lands / which theyr High Might: hitherto ſo laudably / and with ſo difficile warres have maintained / and further / with the helpe of God / are reſolved to maintaine with goods and blood. And likewiſe that the ſayde Propoſition is repleniſhed with er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and not tollerable in theyr ſtate / drawinge in diſpute the ſame ſouveraigntie againſt the Fondementale Lawes of this State. And therefore theyr High Might: kan not allowe ſuch an uniuſt / anlooked / and unneygbourly Propoſition nor approove the ſame / as implikinge an intollerable atrocite againſt theyr ſtate / and to great diſhonour of al Monarches / Kings / Potentates / and Republiques / who haue handled with them as with a Souveraine State. But muſt and neceſſarely declare / that all they / which by any Propoſitions or other meanes / preſume to drawe into diſpute the Souverayne Right of theſe lands / or to impugne the ſame / or to appropriate it to any other Princes / or any thinge that favoured of it / ſhall bee holden and keept as inhabil to bee admitted by theyr High. Might: to any Treatiſe. And this they give the ſayde Lord Peckio for anſwer / onely adding / that the ſayd Archidukes / by the manifold complainctes done unto them / and whereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no ſatiſfaction is done / knowe ſufficiently / how theyr High. Mightines underſtande that the Treatiſe of Truce poinctly and regiliouſly by them and the Kinge of Spaine ſhould be keept. Actum in the congregation of the ſayd General States in the Hague the 25. of March. 1621. And was paragraphed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henr. ter Coulen, Vidit.</signed> Onder ſtoot / <hi>By Ordinance of the Sayd General States.</hi> 
               <signed>And was ſubſcribed. <hi>C. Aerſſen.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
